CHAPTER 2

Hindi Cinema and Caste Question
Ideology and Reproduction of Dominance

MANOJ KUMAR JENA

INTRODUCTION

Cinema evolved out of photographic and sound technology as well as the convergence of all techniques and skills of artistic form. Cinema also incorporates different technologies in production, including cinematography, editing, location and sound. Its main form is cinematography, which expedites the process of visual storytelling to the audience with sound. It is an expressive art of reality and imagination. Stanley Cavell (1979) argues that ‘the world of moving picture is screened’. He also argues that ‘the screen is a frame; the frame is the whole field of the screen—as a frame of film is the whole field of a photograph, like the frame of a loom or a house’.1 As Gilles Deleuze rightly said, ‘the cinema does not just present images; it surrounds them with a world’.2 Cinema, as a powerful communicative medium carrying messages with embedded meaning, can influence the mind, body and soul of any individual and community at large. Cinema is a reflector of social reality; it mirrors the social transformations, cultural relations/tensions and new trends that are surfacing in society in significant ways. ‘The history of cinema aligned early on with the epistemic and pragmatic concerns of industrial labour and capital accumulation. Not surprisingly, one of the first films made by Auguste and Louis Lumière—the Frenchmen known for their invention of the cinématographe—portrayed a group of workers (mostly females) marching out the gate to the brothers’ factory in the Lyon suburbs’.3 ‘Moving pictures appeared in the major cities of the British Empire in the late nineteenth century, while they were being introduced in Europe and North America. Over the first two decades of the twentieth century, the medium spread from the large urban centres of the West Indies, India, southern Africa, and British Malaya into provincial towns and villages. By the end of the First World War, ‘going to the pictures’ had become a fixture of public leisure for hundreds of thousands of imperial subjects, who were seeing movies in a wide array of urban and rural venues’.4

Cinema is a vital adjunct of the public sphere moulding the views, attitudes and opinions of the vast movie-going public.5 Furthermore, cinema establishes a relationship between capital and consumers; content craters are producers (capital), and audiences are sometimes seen as potential consumers in the cinema industry. Cinematic expression has always been associated with culture, language, myth, experience, and desire and has also reinforced belief, morality, ethics and work as a persuasive instrumental role in society at large. Cinema/Movies/Films often function in an ideological role in society where cinematic content carries a specific kind of meaning and fosters a particular state of mind. Movies, which carry images through cinematic production, further influence audiences at both conscious and unconscious levels. There has been a strong connection between cinema and public culture since the very beginning of the industrialization and modernization process in the West and India. In India, cinema has been playing a vital role in disseminating an urban consciousness; facilitating the transition from feudal and agricultural societies to urban and industrial societies; and from there to consumer and postmodernist societies. Cinema has been a facilitator of social transformation in India in complex ways.6 The cinematic medium influences and shapes public opinion and is also oriented toward public awareness and concern with public issues. Cinema has modified and reinforced structural change, maintaining and redefining cultural traits and patterns in society at large and further bringing structural transformation within and outside of society. Media commentators argue that the development of Media/ Movies/Cinema is interlinked with institutional transformation, which is one of the factors shaping modern society. In this context the chapter studies Hindi Cinema from a sociological vantage point, particularly Hindi cinema has also been studied as an institution and art form, as well as for its social, cultural and ideological role in society. Additionally, the chapter tries to understand narration, image/photography, the power of visual imagery, technology and creative processes. Furthermore, it has addressed the questions of ideology and reproduction of caste domination in Hindi Cinema.

Sociology of Cinema and Society:
Culture and Consciousness

As discussed earlier, Cinema is an integral and embedded aspect of our social life and can be seen as a taken-for-granted reality for many people. In modern industrial settings, Cinema/Movies are perceived as text and medium and are associated with technology that is evolving every other day. Cinematic production has always been intertwined with our sociocultural and political imagination, including economic activities. As Turner argues, Cinema is integrated with larger cultural production. ‘Culture’ came to be redefined as the processes that construct a society’s way of life: its systems for producing meaning, sense, or consciousness, especially those systems and media of representation that give images their cultural significance.7 Likewise, consciousness itself thus results from a relationship between identification with and the taking in or introjection of signs (like a name), terms, and concepts that shape and mould behaviours and identity. Signs and symbols are thus the hallmark of consciousness more than some essence of personhood.8 Whether it is cinema, theatre, literature, the printing press, or television to the internet, all communicative media are integral parts of the cultural system. It not only reverberates our thought categories but also enhances and enables us to interpret, reinterpret, perceive and know about ourselves and others. Moreover, it functioned as an amplifier in a time-space sequence. Various forms of media, including symbols, signs, language, literature, images, and visual imagery, are the most dominant and determinant powerful forces for bringing change in society. For Graeme Turner (1999), ‘Film as a social practice, and the understanding of its production and consumption, its pleasures and its meanings, is enclosed within the study of the workings of culture itself ’.9 His argument centred around the social process of making images, sounds and signs.

Cinema/movies have always been an enabling factor for new forms of social action within and outside geographical boundaries, and they have a large global impact. Siegfried Kracauer argues that ‘Film actually reproduces the raw material of the physical world within the work of art’.10 It is a cultural product and is shaped by the inner dimension of individual life, even community life at large. One can analyse from Adorno, Fromm, Horkheimer and Marcuse’s points of view the socio-psychological dimension of relations between individuals and culture in particular.11 One can comprehend, how there is a direct link between people’s lives and cultural context. Therefore, to argue, Cinema shapes perception with a specific ideological base to form and conform to the submissive self. One can argue that Cinema produces particular kinds of self that are subservient to the dominant system. They are passive consumers and saleable products. One can perceive how the cultural domination of Hindi cinema produces a subservient and passive self when it is marginal. What Adorno argues about the end of individualism in the contemporary period. In a critical sense, the contemporary order overpowers individuals through standardized, monotonous mass culture, leaving little room for genuine individualism. The cinema and culture industry essentially fulfils all the need for control and repression. Cinema also gives rise to different kinds of authoritarian structures, cultivating particular types of what Horkheimer and Adorno called ‘Sado-masochistic character’.12 Contemporary cinema produces and reproduces dominant characters normalizing violence and subjugation through various genres.

In the contemporary phase, the gravity, intensity and reach of media, particularly cinema, have strengthened in many ways. It not only mediates social relationships but also takes the front stage to socialize every aspect of life. The social structure and process are encompassed by the culture of mediation, which is embedded with messages and meaning. Various media outlets are continuously disseminating information and misinformation, to sizeable and diversified audiences in Indian society. These messages certainly influence many aspects of social, political and economic patterns.

Cinematic Power, Image and Meaning

As in any human relationship projected on a screen, film narratives are mostly subject to the complexity, spontaneity, and level of sophistication that the relation with the ‘other’ requires.13 Cinematic significance is associated with the combination of the camera technique of framing, the angle of the camera, the depth of field, the composition and the size of the aperture. Similarly, for Turner, images, as well as words, carry connotations. A filmed image of a man will have a denotative dimension—it will refer to the mental concept of ‘man’. However, images are culturally charged; the camera angle employed, his position within the frame, the use of lighting to highlight certain aspects, and any effect achieved by colour, tinting, or processing all have the potential for social meaning. When we deal with images, it is especially apparent that we are not only dealing with the object or the concept they represent but also dealing with how they are represented.14

Camera angles can identify a shot with a character’s point of view by taking a position that corresponds to that which we imagine the particular character would be occupying. We see what the character would be seeing.15 The camera can be viewed as a power of mingling with an image, and the movement of an image is connected with cinematic expression. In Hindi Movies, the position of the camera angle represents the dominant position of a particular person who represents the upper echelon of society. Representation of a particular marginal image on a cinematic screen reproduces identical cultural traits for instance, about their livelihood, appearance, location and occupation. Cinematic narration is another powerful element of a cinematic screen. Which influenced the audience’s mind? Within a specific period, audience engagement with the silver screen establishes intrinsic bonding. In the dark room, which is only on a silver screen, cinema narrates the story that the audience assumes to be the real story and not the reel story. In this situation, individuals are completely engrossed with the sound, image and frame of the cinematic screen. Cinema narrates and tells a story about our physical and existential world. However, who tells the story in what context and to whom matters a lot. This question prevents all media sociologists from answering how this happens. ‘Film is uniquely equipped to record and reveal physical reality and hence gravitates towards it’.16 According to Turner,

With the development of cinematic technique, a screen became a power source where the life on the screen was life and the audience engages themselves with this powerful expressive medium. Therefore, the film incorporates the separate technologies and discourses of the camera, lighting, editing, set design, and sound—all contributing to the meaning.17 Furthermore, ‘the positioning of the camera is possibly the most apparent of the practices and technologies which contribute to the making of a film’.18

Hindi Cinema and the Emergence of a
Dominant Cultural System

The Indian cinema industry, which is now the largest in the world in terms of the quantity of output, has traversed a long course, marked by the forgotten efforts of countless people and the faded signs of innumerable phases and trends.19 Hindi Cinema (popularly known as Bollywood cinema) is one of the dominant language cinema types in India and has influenced our perceptions of culture and the construction of cinematic reality. Indian cinema is diverse in terms of language and cultural setting. Cinema is produced in various languages in India, ranging from Jammu & Kashmir to Tamil Nadu and from Gujarat to Assam. India is the largest producer of cinema in South Asia.

The Bombay film/Hindi Film industry is aesthetically and culturally distinct from Hollywood, but as prolific and ubiquitous in its production and circulation of narratives and images. As the dominant media institution within India, the Bombay film industry plays an important role in constructing and defining dichotomies such as ‘traditional/modern’, ‘global/local’, ‘Western/ Eastern’ and categories such as ‘culture’, ‘nation’, and ‘Indian’.20

The history of the Indian film industry is quite fascinating. Cinema arrived in India at a time when rapid population growth was creating an archipelago of sprawling, polyglot metropolises across the subcontinent. These cities are remarkable for their ethnic, religious, and cultural diversity.21 Cinematic screens have a long history in India. Cinema was shown for the first time in India by the Lumière brothers on 7 July 1896 at the Watson Hotel in Mumbai. This was just six months after the first show in Paris (the Lumière brothers who invented the cinematography started the projection of short films for the Parisian public on 28 November 1895).22 The Times of India glowingly referred to it as the ‘miracle of the century’. Westerners, who were quick to realize the value of India as a site of filmmaking because of both its natural beauty and its ‘exotic’ culture, were inspired to make films that used Indian scenery and culture—for example, Coconut Fair (1897), Our Indian Empire (1897), A Panorama of Indian Scenes and Procession (1898) and Poona Races ‘98’ (1898).23 The earliest short films to be photographed in India were by unknown foreign cameramen in 1897. An Indian ventured to make his short films in 1899. India’s first narrative feature came in 1912. The Indian talkie film arrived in 1931.24

In India, at least 80 per cent of films shown in the late 1920s were American, even though twenty-one studios manufactured local films, eight or nine of them in regular production. Although its narrow range of distribution restricted its cinematic and social influence, Indian film production later burgeoned, with production levels exceeding those of any other country, including the United States, from the 1970s on.25

The Hindi movies content is distinct in terms of its ‘linguistic, regional, religious, and caste origins and the identities of its members; what is striking is the intensification of kinship networks within the contemporary industry’.26 Hindi Cinema/Movies in India has been considered a dominant, influential and persuasive medium since the very beginning, in fact since the production and release of Raja Harischandra by Dadasaheb Dhandiraj Govindraj Phalke on 3 May 1913. Hindi Cinema Industry has extended its tentacle; one may view it as an ‘ideological octopus’ in and around both the Hindi-speaking and non-Hindi-speaking states of India. The Hindi Cinema industry is one of the prominent infotainment mediums for the general masses as it produces various genres of movies each year. The Hindi Movies elucidate contrasting realities and myriad circumstances carrying contradicting meaning. Movies also bring cinematic genres of various kinds. Samir Dayal argues that ‘Hindi cinema has been, to change metaphors, a dream machine, producing images of collective or national identity that, with every iteration, prove more transitional, contradictory, and elusive or enable us to screen truths about ourselves from ourselves’.27 Hindi cinema, is particularly, popular or ‘hit’ films, stars and songs, irrespective of their artistic merits. These films have become part of contemporary Indian folklore. The songs in them are sung by generations, the idioms used by millions of people.28 Bollywood, particularly Hindi cinema, controls the culture, language, and style idioms of everyday imaginary of individuals. The viewers are perpetually influenced by Bollywood cinema, which has an enormous impact on larger Hindi and non-Hindi audiences.

Ideology and Cinematic Communication:
Reproduction of Caste/Class Domination

It is argued that Hindi Cinematic communication produces a dominant ideological pattern that negates marginal subjects. Ideology arises in association with processes of communication and exchange. Ideology involves the reproduction of the existing relations of production. Ideology operates as a constraint, limiting us to certain places or positions within these processes of communication and exchange.29 Furthermore, ideology refers to sets of ideas that give some account of the social world; ideas that are usually partial (in both senses) or selective (as all positions are); and the relationship of these ideas or values to how power is distributed socially.30

Marx and Engel argue that ruling ideas are nothing more than the ideal expression of dominant material relations; the dominant material relations grasped as ideas; hence of the relations which make the one class the ruling one, therefore the idea of its dominance.31

For Raymond Williams (1977), ideology is defined as (i) a system of beliefs characteristic of a particular class or group, (ii) a system of illusory beliefs—false ideas or false consciousness—which can be contrasted with true or scientific knowledge; (iii) the general process of the production of meanings and ideas.32

From William’s point of view, Hindi cinema produces a particular dominant kind of belief pattern of upper class/caste essence and appearance.

Alen Swingewood argues

ideology becomes of crucial importance for the value associated with mass production and consumption of comics, pulp fiction and newspapers combine effect of television, cinema and radio corrupt and deradicalize the proletariat. For him sociologically mass society lacking strong, independent social groups and institutions, a society dominated from above.33

For Bill Nichols, ideology uses the fabrication of images and the processes of representation to persuade us how things are, how they ought to be and that the place provided for us is the place we ought to have.34 For Althusser ideology is associated with Ideological State Apparatuses. For him, ‘The Ideological State Apparatuses (ISA) function massively and predominantly by ideology, but they also function secondarily by repression, even if ultimately, but only ultimately, this is very attenuated and concealed, even symbolic.’35 Bill argues, ‘the dominant ideology, representing the ideas of the dominant class to perpetuate its dominance through the psychic and material investments we are led to make as signs of acquiescence, has the upper hand.’36 Most ‘Ideological theories stress that all communication and all meanings have a socio-political dimension and that they cannot be understood outside their social context. This ideological work always favours the status quo, for the classes with power dominate the production and distribution not only of goods but also of ideas and meanings’.37 In a sense Hindi Cinema industry is in a vortex of the Class and Caste nexus, the meaning and ideas produced largely from dominant caste/class perspectives with ideological domination. The economic system is organized in their interest, and the ideological system derives from it and works to promote, naturalize, and disguise it. Whatever their differences, all ideological theories agree that ideology works to maintain class domination38. One can see in the Indian context how ideology maintains class and caste domination. For instance, the production of specific ideological cinema is making the individual a passive recipient, what Herbert Marcuse argues about one-dimensional thought which eliminates alternative ideas, may be encouraging exploitative practices. Herbert Marcuse also argues that ‘the products indoctrinate and manipulate; they promote a false consciousness which is immune against its falsehood’.39 Marcuse states that idea ‘emerges a pattern of one-dimensional thought and behaviour’.40 One can also see how the logic of caste, capital and cinema is associated with cinematic content and image. Many a time Hindi Cinema is producing one-dimensional content. In fact, hegemoic, hierarchical relations operates in a deep uncouscious level, where the cinematic message and meaning play the lead role. It furtherance ‘repressive structuring’, which Marcuse called ‘surplus repression’, because of asymmetric relations of power through the exploitative process.41 Cinema can be seen as a force of cultural domination; from Marcuse’s point of view, in the age of mass consumerism and popular culture, a new social order has emerged that sharply curtails individuality, dissent and opposition.42

As Jean-Louis Baudry puts it,

[cinema] constitutes the subject by the illusory delimitation of a central location—whether this be that of a God or of any other substitute. It is an apparatus destined to obtain a precise ideological effect, necessary to the dominant ideology: creating a fantasmatization of the subject, it collaborates with a marked efficacy in the maintenance of idealism.43

Movies/Cinema can appeal to the imagination and engage in emotions; the viewer may not only watch the unfolding screenplay but also participate in it. S/he will often identify with one of the characters, and the result of the experience may be that the viewer may learn something about what he/she feels like to stand in the shoes of a person of a different time, nationality, ethnic group, or other situation vastly dissimilar to his or her own (such as a lower-class ghetto).44 Cinema factory also exercise power over individuals through various genres, and individuals internalize structures and reproduce them the same way. The power structure is caste- and class-specific and governs the industry and its relationships. Cinema can be seen as the ‘product of social conditioning’.45 It is embedded with a hegemonic group of capitalist cine players. Additionally, the audience has varying degrees of freedom to construct relationships with the individual texts of the medium or with the medium as a whole. Individuals can deeply move (for better or worse) by what they see and hear on the screen.46 Social order is thus augmented by the ideological domination of a ruling class that effectively controls and, in many cases, owns the mass media.47

Most of the Hindi movies portrayed kinds of stereotyped ideals and images of Marginals particularly Scheduled Caste. Historically, Marginals, particularly Scheduled Caste/Dalit, are composed of mostly exploited, discriminated and subjugated people in India. For a very long time, this group was systematically excluded from the cinematic production process as well as from larger cultural production processes, including those in the cultural sphere. It is perceived that Hindi movies reproduce hegemonic dominant cultural traits that contradict Marginal life. Caste discrimination, subjugation and exploitation, as well as normalization of violence, can be observed in contemporary Hindi cinematic images; for instance, Aakrosh (2010) and Chauranga (2014) to Article 15 (2019). The construction of the stereotype Marginal/Dalit identity is nurtured and cultivated continuously on the Hindi Cinematic screen. Caste/Class feudal and hegemonic domination is visible in the cinematic production of content. The ideology used in cinema is primarily concerned with specific kinds of dominant ideas and values; specifically, the image of the oppressor has been internalized and homogenized through cinematic content. Paulo Freire rightly argued that the oppressed, having internalized the image of the oppressor and adopting his guidelines, are fearful of freedom.48 Paulo Freire further argues that cultural invasion is, on the one hand, an instrument of domination and, on the other hand, the result of domination; furthermore, cultural invasion serves the ends of conquest and the preservation of oppression.49 One can see how contemporary hegemonic Hindi cinema has invaded the entire cultural sphere of marginals. Hindi Cinema combines domination, self, identity and the significance of one’s emotional life. It much more reverberates with fictitious ecstasy, false pleasure and repression. Therefore, the content of the cinema needs to be analysed and understood through the ideology and political economy of the Hindi Cinema industry. The following questions arise: who is the producer and controller of the medium, message and meaning, and how is it emotionally significant? One cannot negate the psychological impact of content and image. From the psychoanalytic perspective of the unconscious, selfhood socialization is linked with cinematic production, which is also a critical question for Hindi Cinema. Frankfurt school theorist Adorno and others have argued that psychoanalysis and identity formation can be contextualized in the context of cinema. From Jacques Lacan’s point of view, the realm of ideology through traumatic film encounters the real. The issue of power is central to this text, as is the imbricated issue of powerlessness or jouissance.50 How the script writer or cinematic product creates content that reflects the internal landscape of identity formation impacts cultural and social relations. Cinema also plays a central ideological role in practice and products and is also a source of conformation of inequality in society. The caste inequality is reproduced and translated in movie messages and media practices. As earlier argued Hindi Cinema is associated with a larger logic of caste and capital structure, and the content of Hindi Cinema serves a specific caste/class interest. Many a time, Hindi movies produce one-dimensional cinema and hesitate to challenge the dominant ideology. Few movies have attempted to challenge domination but have faced numerous impediments.

For instance, Sanjiv Jaiswal, maker of Shudra: The Rising and Quota: The Reservation, back in 2012, narrates his experience as an alternative movie maker.

When we made the film Shudra: The Rising, we faced innumerable challenges and obstacles. After its release, the audience appreciated it, and we even got global acclaim. Our recent film Quota: The Reservation, which was based on Dalit discrimination faced in elite institutions, surpassed expectations and went on to win global awards. However, we did not get screens to give it a theatrical release, owing to the hesitancy still present. Finally, we had to release it on OTT and received much-deserved reach.51

This is a critical issue, as not receiving enough screens, particularly from the distributor side, will create a situation of control and command. Controlling the space is itself as good as controlling public culture as well as messaging and meaning, including the lives of individuals and communities. Many a time message and meaning do not emerge from democratic or social consensus but rather from the dominant class/caste perspective. The prescribed values and ideas are seen as the weapon used by the dominant group over the marginals. For instance, reinforcing stereotypes, enforcing exploitative practices, normalizing violence and suppressing marginals. Caste and class hierarchical ordering of social structure is rooted in Hindi cinematic culture. The world of everyday cinema is embedded with a ‘matrix of domination’,52 particularly a matrix of caste and class domination. Hindi cinematic narratives are an undetached aspect of Indian sociocultural life. Cinema also carries symbolic code and meaning through images and content to denigrate Marginals particularly scheduled castes/Dalits. There is also a ‘language’ for visual representation, sets of codes and conventions used by the audience to make sense of what they see. Many Hindi movies constantly use derogatory language for Dalit’s such as Neech, (Wretched) Neech Jati, for instance, Chauranga (2014), and Article 15 (2019). For instance, Priyadarshan directed Aakrosh’s (2010) storyline, in which the content and image of the movie portray the idea of caste dominance and honour killing. The plot revolves around intercaste marriage, control of women’s bodies, patriarchy and caste discrimination and violence against Dalits. Depiction of the caste killing and hegemony of upper caste/class in India, consciously and unconsciously influence the audience. Priyadarshan’s characterization of dominant caste image particularly the idea of the upper caste hero as the saviour has been normalized in Hindi Cinema. The main protagonist is the upper caste Sidharth Chaturvedi, a Dalit, Major Pratap Kumar a supporting actor, who also suffered through the caste system. Even after having a meritorious career, he could not marry the daughter of the upper caste teacher because of the fear of caste atrocities and subjugation (his father refused due to fear of caste punishment). This movie stereotyped a particular ideological form and identity formation; the images depicted in the movies about Dalits are from Neech, and they are not supposed to drink water from Dudh Kuan (Milk Well); they must take water from Kala Kuan (Dirty/Black Well). Kala Kuan is produced by a specific symbolic system. The binary of Kala Kuan and Dudh Kuan is the depiction of what Louis Dumont called purity and pollution.

Sanjiv Jaiswal’s directorial movie Sudra: The Rising (2012) is a different genre depicting the image of Dalit exploitation and untouchability. This is a historical periodic film and historical analysis of Sudra exploitation. The narration and framing of stories are interesting in many ways. Such as violence and exploitation of Dalit women. This Hindi language film is based on the storyline of the caste system. Exploitation, subjugation and sexual assault of Dalit women. Depiction of agony, pain and suffering. Images and narrations of movies reinforce the unconscious aspects of caste systems. Disturbing images, landless Dalits, and use of work, the film Neech Jati depicts the reality of the caste system in India. Water and sacred wells are important components of movies.

Chauranga (2014), by Bikas Rajan Mishra, depicted the relationships among caste exploitation, women’s bodies and violence against lower caste. It has been observed that many a time, the movie maker stereotyped the scheduled caste with animal considered dirty. They reinforce the lower caste marginal identity with foul and filthy substance. Symbolic representations of Dalits are impure stereotypes in cinemas. This movie depicts the story of reinforcement of subjugation, killing a Dalit boy for writing a love letter to an upper caste girl. Caste profiling and the production of particular caste stereotypes in cinema further reinforce caste discrimination and inequality; for instance, Chauranga (2014) described the image of pig suars and the relationships of pigs with Dalits. Most of the Hindi movies stereotyped specific images about Dalits and constant use and abuse of the words Neech Jati and lower caste, etc., had very strong impact on individuals and the community. It is essential to understand how the upper echelon operates in Indian society through the production of a symbolic cultural system and the formation of identity

Dhadak (2018): This movie was adopted and based on Sairat blockbuster Marathi movie. The story is based on an inter caste love story where a marginal boy falls in love with an upper caste girl whose father is a dominant politician. Finally, the story goes with a fight and struggle for love and life. Ultimately, the father killed the marginal boy and his son. It is depressing and shows a particular way to hegemonies the upper caste ideas. The difference between the two Marathi movies is depicted realistically. It’s story about marginal men and upper-caste women. Dhadak’s end is truly chilling and disturbing the killing of both man and his son; this image itself is disturbing; on the one hand, it depicts the story of the justification of honour killing and on the other killing by Dalits as a normalization phenomenon.

Article 15 (2019): Non Dalit is the protagonist; specifically, the upper caste hero is the saviour. The film is a stereotypical imagination of an upper caste filmmaker, and the imagination lacks the lived reality of Dalits. It is a simplification of the generalized narrative and does not cover the full scope of Dalit emancipation. The frame of the image is completely stereotyped, justifying the dominant ideas that, Sab Barabar Honge to Raja Koun Banega (if everyone is equal who will be the king); for Santulan (balance), the stratification is justifiable.

All these movie narratives are centred around negation, exploitation and subjugation as well as the reproduction of domination. Hindi movies are more or less a one-dimensional cinema that is associated with caste and capital and has been producing a repressive ideology of subjugation rather than emancipation. Nichols rightly argues that ‘Imaginary here does not mean unreal, existing only in the imagination, but rather pertains to views, images, fictions, or representations that contribute to our sense of who we are and to our everyday engagement with the world around us.’53

Contemporary Hindi cinema construct particular kinds of identities. The symbolic code and symbolic system facilitate a particular kind of identity. From Lacan’s point of view, identity is the result of a complex and dialectical relationship between the real conditions of the individual body and the environment, the social-symbolic system that it is situated within, and the individual’s own dynamic history at the juncture of the two. The social-symbolic system thus plays an enormous role in the construction and maintenance of identity.54 The problem of the current cinema consciously and unconsciously negates the emancipation of marginal precisely Dalits. The Dalit has never been a dominant subject; rarely, one finds a Dalit protagonist in the Hindi Cinema. However, to some extent, southern cinema does quite well. Recently, most of the blockbuster Hindi cinema has centred around upper caste/class dominant majoritarian identity. Contemporary blockbuster commercial successful movies produced by various production houses include upper class/caste charters and stories; for instance, Dabangg (2010), Tanu Weds Manu (2011), Dum Laga Ke Haisha (2015), Jolly LLB 2 (2017), Bajrangi Bhaijaan (2015), Badhai Ho (2018), Dream Girl (2019), Article 15 (2019), and Pati Patni Aur Who (2019) mostly represent upper caste/class identity. Dabang (2010) to Article 15 (2019), most of the protagonists carry upper-caste cultural values. In the Lacanian sense, it is reinforcing upper caste/class cultural values in totality. This symbolizes how Indian popular culture is embedded with upper caste/class norms and values. In a certain sense, it reinforces existing caste identities. This also indicates that the upper caste/class identity is the most saleable commodity in the Hindi movie market what Stuart Hall argues about the ‘dominant hegemonic position.’55 This is the normalization of particular cultural identities on the Hindi cinematic screen, essentially by producing, packaging and marketing upper caste/class essence and minimizing marginals. In a sense, Indian cinema reinforces class/caste-centric ideological stereotypes among the national audience, which is antithetical to the life and reality of the marginal. The conditions of marginality in relation to the production of meaning in the cultural sphere is an important question for marginal. Although marginal has had its own cultural text, that text was systematically marginalized through historical exploitation. The lack of substantial representation of Dalits in Hindi Cinema questions cultural rights in public culture. Cultural exclusion of Dalits is a historical question, and the structure has been shaped such that it exploits and excludes Dalits. Even today, visible exploitative practices have a strong historical link with caste structure and functions.

Cinema ideologically constructs the stereotypes of caste hegemony. In the case of Hindi Cinema, the caste/class and capital merged, and the upper caste and class controlled everything; they controlled the medium, message and meaning. In a sense, they are part of the production of messages and meaning. One-dimensional cinema produces a particular ideology bent of mind that negates the alternative.

CONCLUSION

Hindi cinema, is a symbolic system and an institution in India essentially associated with medium, message and meaning. The control of the medium, power of messaging and meaning is a crucial factor in the cinema industry in India. It has been observed that Hindi Cinema storylines are centred around upper class/caste narratives. It reproduces a specific class and caste ideology. In Althusers sense it is ideological state apparatus. The political economy of the Hindi film industry encompasses and represents the upper echelon of the Indian social structure. The Hindi cinema storytellers and production houses are always glorifying upper class/caste ideas. The cinematic medium represents the essence and appearance of the upper strata of society. It has been observed that for a long, most of the blockbusters (maximum viewership) have essentially propagated upper class/caste normative order.

Hindi movies do not dare to break ideological domination. Repression, subjugation and violence against Dalits is routinely normalized in cinematic reels. The representation of violence and subjugation reinforce similar kinds of stereotypes in different locations. Moreover, contemporary content writers do not dare to break stereotypes but rather reinforce them. However, there are exceptions in the case of cinema in southern India, which try to break dominant ideological barriers, for instance, Pa. Ranjith’s Kaala (2018).

NOTES

1. Stanley Cavell. The World Viewed: Reflections on the Ontology of Film, enlarged edition (1979), Harvard University Press.

2. Gilles Deleuze. Cinema 2: The Time-Image, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, 1989.

3. Pasi Väliaho. ‘The Brain’s Labour: On Marxism and The Movies’. In The Anthem Handbook of Screen Theory, edited by Hunter Vaughan and Tom Conley. London: Anthem Press, 2018.

4. James Burns (2013). Cinema and Society in the British Empire, 1895-1940, New York: Palgrave Macmillan.

5. K. Moti Gokulsing and Wimal Dissanayake. Routledge Handbook of Indian Cinemas, Routledge (2013).

6. Ibid.

7. Graeme Turner (1988). Film as Social Practice, London: Routledge.

8. Vincent F. Rocchio. Reel Racism: Confronting Hollywood’s Construction of Afro-American Culture, Westview Press: Colorado, 2000.

9. Graeme Turner, Film as Social Practice (Studies in Culture and Communication), Routledge (1999).

10. Cited in Gerald Mast, Marshall Cohen and Leo Braudy (1992), Film Theory and Criticism: Introductory Readings (1992, OUP), New York.

11. Please see T.B. Bottomore, Frankfurt School.

12. Max Horkheimer and Theodor W. Adorno. Dialectic of Enlightenment: Philosophical Fragments, Stanford University Press, 2002.

13. Rémi Fournier Lanzoni, French Comedy on Screen: A Cinematic History (Palgrave Macmillan, 2014).

14. Graeme Turner (1988). Film as Social Practice. London: Routledge.

15. Ibid.

16. Marshall Cohen, Leo Braudy (1992), Film Theory and Criticism: Introductory Readings (1992, OUP), New York.

17. Graeme Turner (1988). Film as Social Practice. London: Routledge.

18. Ibid.

19. Firoze Rangoonwalla, 75 Years of Indian Cinema, New Delhi: Indian Book Company, 1975.

20. T. Ganti (2000). ‘Casting Culture: The Social Life of Hindi Film Production in Contemporary India’, unpublished PhD dissertation, New York University.

21. James Burns (2013). Cinema and Society in the British Empire, 1895-1940, New York: Palgrave Macmillan.

22. J.V. Vilanilam, Growth and Development of Mass Communication in India, New Delhi: NBT, 2003.

23. K. Moti Gokulsing and Wimal Dissanayake, Indian Popular Cinema—A Narrative of Cultural Change, London: Trenthan Book, 1998.

24. Firoze Rangoonwalla, 75 Years of Indian Cinema, New Delhi: Indian Book Company, 1975.

25. Ruth Vasey. The Worldwide Spread of Cinema, The Oxford History of World Cinema, edited by Geoffrey Nowell-Smith, OUP, New York, 1996.

26. T. Ganti (2004). Bollywood: A Guidebook to Popular Hindi Cinema, New York: Routledge.

27. Samir Dayal, Dream Machine: Realism and Fantasy in Hindi Cinema, Temple University Press (2015), Philadelphia.

28. Akbar S. Ahmed, ‘Bombay Films: The Cinema as Metaphor for Indian Society and Politics’, Modern Asian Studies, vol. 26, no. 2, May 1992, pp. 289-320.

29. Bill Nichols, Ideology and the Image Social Representation in the Cinema and Other Media, Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1981.

30. Gill Branston with Roy Stafford, The Media Student’s Book, 5th edn., Oxon: Routledge, 2010.

31. Marx and Engles, On Literature and Art, Moscow: Progress Publishers, 1978.

32. Raymond Williams, Marxism and Literature, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1977.

33. Alan Swingewood, The Myth of Mass Culture. London: Macmillan, 1977, p. 11.

34. Bill Nichols, Ideology and the Image: Social Representation in the Cinema and Other Media, Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1981.

35 https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/althusser/1970/ideology.htm

36. Bill Nichols, Ideology and the Image: Social Representation in the Cinema and Other Media, Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1981.

37. John Fiske. Introduction to Communication Studies, 2nd edn., New York: Routledge, 1990.

38. Ibid.

39. Herbert Marcuse, One-Dimensional Man: Studies in the Ideology of Advanced Industrial Society, United Kingdom: Routledge & Kegan Paul, 1964, p. 14.

40. Ibid.

41. Ibid.

42. Ibid.

43. Baudry, J.-L. (1985). ‘Basic Effects of the Cinematographic Apparatus’, in Movies and Methods, vol. 2, ed. B. Nichols, pp. 531-42. Berkeley: University of California Press.

44. C. Emory Burton, ‘Sociology and the Feature Film’, Teaching Sociology, vol. 16, no. 3, July 1988, pp. 263-71.

45. Bourdieu, Other Words, p. 116.

46. Roger Silverstone, Television and Everyday Life, London: Routledge, 1994, p. 133.

47. Alan Swingewood, The Myth of Mass Culture, London: Macmillan, 1977, p. 74.

48. Paulo Freire, Pedagogy of the Oppressed, London: Penguin Books, 1996, p. 29.

49. Ibid., pp. 135, 141

50. Todd McGowan, Sheila Kunkle, eds., Lacan and Contemporary Film, Other Press (2004) (Preface).

51. Sanjiv Jaiswal talk to Prateek Sur https://www.outlookindia.com/art-entertainment/rewriting-the-history-of-dalits-and-lower-caste-in-cinema-news-204509

52. Please see Patricia Hill Collins.

53. Bill Nichols, Ideology and the Image: Social Representation in the Cinema and Other Media, Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1981.

54. Vincent F. Rocchio, Reel Racism: Confronting Hollywood’s Construction of Afro-American Culture, Colorado: Westview Press, 2000, p. 18.

55. Stuart Hall. Encoding Decoding in the Television Discourse. University of Birmingham: Center for Cultural Studies, 1973.

REFERENCES

Burns, J. (2013). Cinema and Society in the British Empire, 1895-1940, New York: Palgrave Macmillan

Ganti, T. (2000). ‘Casting Culture: The Social Life of Hindi Film Production in Contemporary India’, unpublished PhD dissertation, New York University.

——. (2004). Bollywood: A Guidebook to Popular Hindi Cinema. New York: Routledge.

Hall, S. (1973). Encoding Decoding in the Television Discourse. University of Birmingham: Center for Cultural Studies, 1973.

John Fiske, J. (1990). Introduction to Communication Studies, 2nd edn., New York: Routledge.

Nichols, B. (1981). Ideology and the Image: Social Representation in the Cinema and Other Media. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1981.

Swingewood, A. (1977). The Myth of Mass Culture. London: Macmillan, 1977, p 11.

Turner, Graeme (1988). Film as Social Practice. London: Routledge.

Vilanilam, J.V. (2003). Growth and Development of Mass Communication in India, Delhi: NBT, 2003.